It's actually quite straightforward to make your apps content provider
available to third party apps. The key is to modify
the export flag in the manifest entry here to true.
As simple as that. Any app that knows the content URI
can use the content resolve or access it the same
that you do. Now depending on the sensitivity of your
data, you may want to protect it by requiring specific
permissions to read or write to the database. So if you
want to, you can effectively limit access only to other
apps you have created, or to third party apps, which know
the permissions and users agree to. Then you just need to
publish this contract, to interact with the content provider, specifically the
URI and column names. And you've created a simple API
for all of your data. And as simple as that, you've
created a new API, just for your data. This is exactly
the same approach, used by many of the native content providers,
including the Contacts Database, Media Store, Calendar and Call Log.